<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Nico's Lab]]></title><description><![CDATA[Experiences and thoughts of a developer who enjoys functional programming and aspires to game design.]]></description><link>https://nglab.pro</link><image><url>https://nglab.pro/icon.png</url><title>Nico&apos;s Lab</title><link>https://nglab.pro</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 16:48:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nglab.pro/en/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 16:48:50 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[2022 Nicolas Gasull]]></copyright><language><![CDATA[en]]></language><managingEditor><![CDATA[ng@nglab.pro]]></managingEditor><webMaster><![CDATA[ng@nglab.pro]]></webMaster><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[How to simply use vim across multiple files]]></title><description><![CDATA[<section id="preamble" aria-label="Preamble"><p>Vim provides its own <strong>unique</strong> way to edit code. Discerning what makes it really different helps a lot figuring out why so many developers love vim. This article attempts to summarize these core concepts and provides a reasonable set of tips for an efficient use of <strong>vim across multiple files</strong>.</p>
<p>Nowadays, developers that are invited to vim are being told to install all these cool plugins. Although most of these are very good, I believe <strong>plugins make vim’s actual learning curve steeper</strong> than it should be. Some plugins disguise vim into vscode, reminding features like <a href="https://github.com/scrooloose/nerdtree">file explorer toolbar</a> or <a href="https://github.com/mihaifm/bufstop">tabs</a>.</p>
<p>Because vim is harder to grasp when beginning, limiting the number of plugins is crucial. With its core concepts only, <strong>vim already comes with great power and great responsibility</strong>. People probably don’t accept this well enough, at least I didn’t and my resulting experience of vim has been years of trying to stick to it and falling back to another editor (or IDE). It’s time to transform this vim hassle into vim power!</p>
<aside class="admonition-block note" role="note"><h6 class="block-title label-only"><span class="title-label">📎 Note: </span></h6><p>This article assumes the reader already has basic vim knowledge. When mentioning commands, <code>&lt;C-key&gt;</code> means <kbd class="keyseq"><kbd class="key">Ctrl</kbd>+<kbd class="key">key</kbd></kbd>. Capitalization of letters is meaningful as it implies pressing <em>shift</em> at the same time.</p></aside></section>
<nav id="toc" class="toc" role="doc-toc"><h2 id="toc-title">Summary</h2><ol class="toc-list level-1"><li><a href="#_buffers">Buffers</a><ol class="toc-list level-2"><li><a href="#_opening_files">Opening files</a></li><li><a href="#_explore_files">Explore files</a></li><li><a href="#_navigating_across_buffers">Navigating across buffers</a></li><li><a href="#_closing_buffers">Closing buffers</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#_windows">Windows</a></li><li><a href="#_cheatsheet_tldr">Cheatsheet <em>(tl;dr)</em></a></li></ol></nav>
<section class="doc-section level-1"><h2 id="_buffers">Buffers</h2><p>First of all, it’s time to <strong>forget about tabs</strong>. In vim, tabs are a power-user feature that may be useful for those who already master buffers and in very specific scenario. Buffers alone are more than enough. Also, no plugin will put vscode’s tabs in vim.</p>
<p>Experienced vim users often refer to navigating through files as <em>flowing through buffers</em>. Indeed, when you need to access a piece of code, you just place your cursor in it to explore or edit it. There is <strong>no need to care about which buffer is open and where it is</strong>. We’ll see that with just a few commands we are able to keep as many buffers open as we like while still keep editing efficiently!</p>
<section class="doc-section level-2"><h3 id="_opening_files">Opening files</h3><p><strong><code>:find path/file</code></strong> opens <code>path/file</code>. <code>:find</code> supports quick file search if we enable it, so let’s run / add to .vimrc the following commands in order to get comfortable:</p>
<div class="listing-block"><pre class="highlightjs highlight"><code class="language-vim hljs" data-lang="vim"><span class="hljs-keyword">set</span> path+=*
<span class="hljs-keyword">set</span> wildmenu
<span class="hljs-comment">" Optionally ignore bulky folders:</span>
<span class="hljs-keyword">set</span> wildignore+=*/node_modules/*</code></pre></div>
<p>We’ve just set up quick file search! Tab completion now finds files deep in current working directory. For example, <code>:find foobar&lt;Tab&gt;</code> or <code>:find *.ht&lt;Tab&gt;</code> will both find <code>some/nested/dir/foobarbaz.html</code>. If multiple files match, the <em>wildmenu</em> we just enabled appears on top on the command line and more <code>&lt;Tab&gt;</code> presses rotate across matches.</p></section>
<section class="doc-section level-2"><h3 id="_explore_files">Explore files</h3><p>Running <strong><code>:find</code> on a folder</strong> opens <em>netrw</em>, a simple yet efficient file explorer. It provides a tree view if you hit <code>l</code> a few times! You can also create a new file by hitting <code>%</code>, delete with <code>D</code> and rename with <code>R</code>. Using <code>:find</code> alone goes to current file’s directory and <code>:find .</code> goes to current working directory.</p></section>
<section class="doc-section level-2"><h3 id="_navigating_across_buffers">Navigating across buffers</h3><p>A developer’s workflow often involves going back and forth in a code base. Although <code>:find</code> or <a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf.vim">fzf</a> are great for quickly opening files, we can go faster once they have already been opened in buffers.</p>
<div class="ulist"><ul><li><kbd class="keyseq"><kbd class="key">Ctrl</kbd>+<kbd class="key">6</kbd></kbd> swaps to last opened buffer</li><li><kbd class="keyseq"><kbd class="key">Ctrl</kbd>+<kbd class="key">o</kbd></kbd> moves the cursor to the previous location it last <em>jumped</em> from</li><li><kbd class="keyseq"><kbd class="key">Ctrl</kbd>+<kbd class="key">i</kbd></kbd> moves the cursor to the next <em>jump</em></li></ul></div>
<p>The two latter commands take advantage of the <a href="https://vim.fandom.com/wiki/Jumping_to_previously_visited_locations">jumplist</a> which contains all cursor <em>jumps</em>, including inside the same buffer. This is much more powerful than just "tab switching" in other editors as you can extremely quicky jump back and forth more precise contexts. Although they are precise, they might take you more time than a simple <code>Ctrl-6</code> swap-back or than moving away with a quick <code>:find</code> or <em>fzf</em>.</p></section>
<section class="doc-section level-2"><h3 id="_closing_buffers">Closing buffers</h3><p>It won’t cause any trouble to keep any number of buffers open and it is often recommended to keep them open. However, when we mainly rely on <code>Ctrl-o</code>/<code>Ctrl-i</code> to navigate, we want to keep the jumplist history clean. So if, for example, a file has been opened by mistake, all what is needed is <strong><code>:bw</code></strong>.</p></section></section>
<section class="doc-section level-1"><h2 id="_windows">Windows</h2><p>Windows are viewports on a buffer. A single one takes all vim’s space when launching the editor. Some commands like <code>:help anything</code> spawn a new window. <code>:q</code> closes current window or the editor when no window remain.</p>
<p>Windows allow to split the editor, which can be done manually with <code>:split</code> and <code>:vsplit</code>. Window-controlling commands are prefixed by <code>&lt;C-w&gt;</code>. For example, <code>&lt;C-w&gt;</code> followed by a direction focuses the nearest window in that direction.</p>
<p>As I don’t need editor splits that much, I won’t get more into details. However I run vim from an instance of tmux which allows to <a href="https://github.com/christoomey/vim-tmux-navigator">seamlessly navigate across split terminals and vim windows</a>, i.e. with the same shortcut: <code>&lt;C&gt;</code> plus a direction. tmux allows much more and I will write a dedicated article about it.</p>
<hr>
<p>That’s all for file navigation in vim, keeping it <strong>simple and mouse-free</strong>! I still recommend to look into <a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf.vim">fzf</a> for fuzzy finding; I bound it to <code>&lt;C-p&gt;</code> to speed up file jumps. I also recommend to install <a href="https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep">ripgrep</a> on your system for recursive directory text searches. <em>fzf.vim</em> automatically picks up on <em>ripgrep</em> and you just need to run <code>:Rg textOrRegex</code> to start using it.</p></section>
<section class="doc-section level-1"><h2 id="_cheatsheet_tldr">Cheatsheet <em>(tl;dr)</em></h2><div class="table-block"><table class="frame-all grid-all stretch"><colgroup><col style="width: 50%;"><col style="width: 50%;"></colgroup><thead><tr><th class="halign-left valign-top">In buffer</th><th class="halign-left valign-top">Action</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:find file</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Open <code>file</code></td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:find directory</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Explore <code>directory</code><br>
                        <code>:find .</code> for root directory</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:find</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Explore current file’s directory</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>&lt;C-6&gt;</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Swap with previous buffer</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>&lt;C-o&gt;</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Jump back</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>&lt;C-i&gt;</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Jump next</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:split</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Split horizontally</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:vsplit</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Split vertically</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>&lt;C-w&gt; direction</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Focus nearest window</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:bw</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Close buffer</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:q</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Close window</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:help anything</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Opens related help in a new window. Often more efficient than searching the internet!</td></tr></tbody></table></div>
<div class="table-block"><table class="frame-all grid-all stretch"><colgroup><col style="width: 50%;"><col style="width: 50%;"></colgroup><thead><tr><th class="halign-left valign-top">In <em>netrw</em></th><th class="halign-left valign-top">Action</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>i</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Change layout<br>
               <em>list &gt; details &gt; ls &gt; tree</em></td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>%</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">New file</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>d</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">New directory</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>R</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Rename file</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>D</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Delete file</td></tr></tbody></table></div>
<div class="table-block"><table class="frame-all grid-all stretch"><colgroup><col style="width: 50%;"><col style="width: 50%;"></colgroup><thead><tr><th class="halign-left valign-top">With plugins</th><th class="halign-left valign-top">Action</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>&lt;C-p&gt;</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Open <a href="https://github.com/junegunn/fzf.vim">fzf</a></td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>&lt;C-direction&gt;</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Focus nearest window or <em>tmux</em> pane</td></tr><tr><td class="halign-left valign-top"><strong><code>:Rg textOrRegex</code></strong></td><td class="halign-left valign-top">Recursive text search with <a href="https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep">ripgrep</a></td></tr></tbody></table></div></section>]]></description><link>https://nglab.pro/simply-efficiently-use-vim-multiple-files</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://nglab.pro/simply-efficiently-use-vim-multiple-files</guid><category><![CDATA[dev]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicolas Gasull]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Making music programmable again]]></title><description><![CDATA[<section id="preamble" aria-label="Preamble"><p>For adepts of retro-gaming who have some foundation in music, retro-gaming music is a nice area to dig into: it has restrictive musicality, which enables to focus on composition and strong auditive identity.
But after weeks or even months of research, I came to realize how sub-developed music synthesis could be in interactive systems like video games.</p>
<p>This article gives some context about how music used to be made in video games,
how game music composition evolved over the years,
and eventually opens some doors to new creative horizons.</p></section>
<nav id="toc" class="toc" role="doc-toc"><h2 id="toc-title">Summary</h2><ol class="toc-list level-1"><li><a href="#_game_music_in_the_90s">Game music in the 90’s</a></li><li><a href="#_modern_music_composition">Modern music composition</a><ol class="toc-list level-2"><li><a href="#_synthesis_from_midi">Synthesis from MIDI</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#_dynamic_music_synthesis_in_2020">Dynamic music synthesis in 2020?</a></li></ol></nav>
<section class="doc-section level-1"><h2 id="_game_music_in_the_90s">Game music in the 90’s</h2><p>Retro games used to synthesize sound on-the-go by the device’s sound chip or card. This is why retro game music is often referred as <strong>chiptune</strong>.
Many artists <a href="http://battleofthebits.org/">still compose chiptune nowadays</a> - maybe because nostalgia, or maybe because chiptune focuses on composition rather than picking and tweaking instruments, effects and mastering.
Anyhow, it’s an amazing discipline for the hobbyist composer!</p>
<figure class="audio-block"><audio src="/res/audio/flamerepellent-sunvox.ogg" controls="">Your browser does not support the audio tag.</audio>
<figcaption>Quick copycat I made based off <a href="https://fearofdark.bandcamp.com/album/the-coffee-zone">Fearofdark’s amazing work ❤️</a></figcaption></figure>
<p>Chiptune is often composed with a <em>tracker</em>.
In a tracker, audio channels are explicitly separated across vertical <strong>tracks</strong>, notes are textually sequenced and can each have its own <strong>instrument</strong> and receive a variety of effects.
Trackers are here to allow composition while enforcing control over audio channels.</p>
<figure class="image-block"><img src="/img/FastTracker2.png" alt="FastTracker2 screenshot">
<figcaption>FastTracker 2, a DOS music tracker</figcaption></figure>
<p>Although many claim the benefits of the tracker layout because of its compactness, I still think it’s rather outdated and prevents picturing the music well. The main alternative layout, the <strong>piano roll</strong>, comes closer to music sheets which are the standard of music composition. Notes can intuitively be spanned across time, and music layers can be "drawn".</p>
<figure class="image-block"><img src="/img/LMMS_PianoRoll.png" alt="LMMS screenshot">
<figcaption>Piano roll in LMMS</figcaption></figure>
<p>Piano rolls are an essential component of many modern <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_audio_workstation">Digital Audio Workstations (DAW)</a>. Although more visual than trackers, different piano rolls might have many varying features between each other, whereas all trackers are mostly the same.
This has an impact on <strong>how little standard piano roll based DAWs</strong> are.</p>
<p>Most trackers produce <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Module_file"><strong>module files</strong></a>. These files basically separate the <strong>instruments</strong> from the <strong>notes</strong> and <strong>effects</strong>.
A consequence from separating the instruments' sound data is that the module file is usually <strong>much smaller</strong> than raw audio data.
Moreover, isolating instruments formalizes the identity of the music’s sounds. It’s a bit like picking an orchestra!</p>
<p>While I love the <em>module</em> format, there are still issues:</p>
<div class="ulist"><ul><li>Each module file contains its own orchestra</li><li>There are many module formats</li><li>No module format is close to being standard</li></ul></div>
<p>Because of these, I don’t see any significant advantage in using module files in video games. Instead, there must be some sort of standard in order to separate instruments from music…​</p></section>
<section class="doc-section level-1"><h2 id="_modern_music_composition">Modern music composition</h2><p>Modern video game music seems to have converged with regular "song" music along with the evolution of DAWs.
Most games embed compressed raw audio data and it makes sense for most game dev studios that have a dedicated musicians.</p>
<p>Producing raw audio gives maximum flexibility in creation: the musician can use and endless variety of instruments, effects, filters, mixes…​ On top of that, raw audio is very easy to play in the game itself and is, of course, standard.</p>
<p>However, for the indie game developer who wants super-dynamic music progressions, for the hobbyist who doesn’t master music that well, or for the studio who wants to enforce strong auditive identity in a game as lean as possible: they have reasons to be frustrated.</p>
<p>Indeed, in a developer’s mind: why not <strong>making music programmatic</strong>? Graphics can easily be, so why not music?</p>
<p>There is a standard for having instruments communicate together and with computers: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIDI"><strong>MIDI</strong></a>. Instead of transferring raw audio, the MIDI protocol consists in transferring <strong>simpler abstract signals</strong> that will be interpretated according to the receiver. For instance, a MIDI signal can consist of a note with a certain velocity, and the next signal most probably is the release of this note (note off). In this scenario, the same MIDI signals can trigger a very loud note with an echo, a quiet sharp note or even be interpretated as VJ lighting changes!</p>
<p>MIDI is the standard abstraction layer for digital music. Signals can be realtime or can be stored in a <em>.mid</em> file (called <em>Standard MIDI File</em> or <strong>SMF</strong>). This gives us strong hopes for programmatic music! Provided a sound synthesis library, lightweight signals can become music.</p>
<section class="doc-section level-2"><h3 id="_synthesis_from_midi">Synthesis from MIDI</h3><p>MIDI now looks like an obvious choice for standard programmatic music.
However I had a hard time finding how to actually play it back from a game.
Most music learning resources and artists point to proprietary solutions, formats, which work for raw audio but removes programmatic freedom.</p>
<figure class="image-block"><img src="/img/Polyphone.png" alt="Polyphone screenshot">
<figcaption>The Polyphone SoundFont editor</figcaption></figure>
<p>The best solutions I found so far rely on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SoundFont"><strong>SoundFonts</strong></a>. Despite being non-standard, they are a well-accepted format to define a <strong>bank of instruments</strong>.
There are some great pieces of software that make great use of SoundFonts for our purpose, notably:</p>
<div class="ulist"><ul><li><a href="https://github.com/freeors/SDL/blob/master/SDL2_mixer-2.0.1/timidity/timidity.c">TiMidity</a>, a basic midi player originally written for SDL back in the days (1995). It evolved into its separate repositories and can be used as a library, but is very limited</li><li><a href="https://github.com/FluidSynth/fluidsynth">FluidSynth</a>, a MIDI synthesis library specifically made to work with SoundFonts and play the music itself. FluidSynth is also easily embeddable in DAWs though a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Virtual_Studio_Technology">VST</a></li></ul></div>
<p>These libraries are amazing tracks to get started! But I’m still astonished by the small enthusiasm they grab.
A consequence of this is how hard it is to leverage the whole capabilities of FluidSynth in a DAW: most DAWs have their own way to manage effects and thus don’t allow to export those as standard MIDI.
Moreover, even if <strong>MIDI+Soundfont</strong> looks like a "standard" combo, I don’t know any good DAW that allows both MIDI composing and SoundFont creation/edition at the same time.</p></section></section>
<section class="doc-section level-1"><h2 id="_dynamic_music_synthesis_in_2020">Dynamic music synthesis in 2020?</h2><p>Now we reach the point of many wonders. It seems like great music technologies from the 90’s still exist but haven’t reached their full potential.
This didn’t prevent music itself to evolve, but what about the way music is used interactively?
There are countless video games out there, and aside massive franchises, very few are known for their music.
Worse than that: there are so few music games or games that integrate music as part of the gameplay.</p>
<p>Despite incredible technology evolutions, I feel like a whole dimension is missing from game development nowadays.
For hobbyists, music creativity should be as accessible as visual arts.
Music-rich games should be able to fit on a cartridge or a floppy disk like back in the days and should have a well-defined auditive identity.</p>
<p>If this article resonates with you too, feel free to share, <a href="https://twitter.com/ngasull/status/1228238628729409536">tweet</a> or <a href="/about#contact-me">reach out to me</a> and I’ll be happy to know what you think and what we can do 🙂 I really believe that the creative community deserves better!</p></section>]]></description><link>https://nglab.pro/making-music-programmable-again</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://nglab.pro/making-music-programmable-again</guid><category><![CDATA[music]]></category><category><![CDATA[gamedev]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Nicolas Gasull]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>